Hi, ברוכים הבאים Bruchim Haba'im and welcome to Hallel הושענא רבה. Hoshanah
Rabbah. We today's דף Daf is קט"ו Kuf Tet Vav 115. We
pick up on קי"ד עמוד ב' Kuf Yud Dalet Amud Bet and
we pick up with
we had just gone through a whole discussion about how we abstract
from the kid goat and its mother's milk to the general sense
of meat and milk and now we pick up with the discussion
which will last us pretty much for the next דף daf and
a half or so. Yes it's ready but it's not I pushed
it several times. No. Yeah fine. Okay yes and which will be
the
discussion about how we learn from the פסוקים Pesukim that talk about
not to cook that we're also talking about not to eat and
even not to derive benefit. So we pick up in the middle
of קי"ד עמוד ב' Kuf Yud Dalet Amud Bet where it says
אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. The line starts with the word
קרא. Kra. It's about exactly halfway down
and we start with two lines above where there's an asterisk at
the beginning of the line. אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi said
רב אשי Rav Ashi מנין לבשר בחלב שאסור באכילה? Minayin le'basar be'chalav
she'asur ba'achilah?
How do you know you can't eat it? It just says not
to cook it. שנאמר She'ne'emar the verse says now we are very
familiar everybody knows of course the right answer is what we've all
read in
רש"י Rashi when we do the פרשה Parsha with רש"י Rashi that
it says three times don't eat meat and milk. One time means
don't cook meat and milk one time means don't cook one time
don't eat one time don't derive benefit. Well okay somebody should have
told the תנאים Tannaim this רש"י Rashi it would have saved them
a lot of effort because actually the תנאים Tannaim have a half
a dozen if not a dozen different ways of learning out the
prohibition of eating and deriving benefit and only one of them is
from the fact that the תורה Torah repeated it three times. So
we are going to look at a couple of different answers to
this question of how we know that you can't eat meat and
milk together. So let's take a look. Not really. Not really. So
אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi מנין לבשר בחלב שאסור באכילה? Minayin
le'basar be'chalav she'asur ba'achilah? How do you know you can't eat them
together? שנאמר She'ne'emar the verse says לא תאכל כל תועבה. Lo tochal
kol to'evah. Do not eat any abomination. So what does that mean?
So see we are interpreting it to mean now that seems to
be an introduction to the forbidden species of animals the non-kosher species.
But now we're abstracting it. כל שתיעבתי לך Kol she'ti'avti lecha
anything that I have abominated to you anything that I have considered
an abomination הרי הוא בבל תאכל. harei hu be'val tochal.
You can't eat it. So therefore what does God consider an abomination?
Presumably if God doesn't want us to cook meat and milk together
so therefore the product of meat and milk is also something that
is not desirable. Maybe even more to the point and we'll see
how the גמרא Gemara abstracts this if it is the product of
a forbidden act so therefore it should also be considered an abomination.
So if I have made abominable to you the act of cooking
it together then the product also should be considered abominable and forbidden
and in the פסוק pasuk of לא תאכל כל תועבה. lo tochal
kol to'evah. So that will lead the גמרא Gemara to ask about
a lot of other products of forbidden acts which are not forbidden
and that will be the most of the discussion at least for
half of the דף daf of קט"ו עמוד א'. Kuf Tet Vav
Amud Aleph. But that's what we are doing we are making this
generic prohibition of not eating things that are abominable here meaning that
it was a product of an act that was forbidden. And let's
read a little bit more. ואין לי אלא באכילה. Ve'ein li ela
ba'achilah. That only tells me not to eat it. בהנאה מנין? Be'hana'ah
minayin? How do you know not to derive benefit? כדירבי אבהו Ked'Rabbi
Abbahu like רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. דאמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר
De'amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Elazar said רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu in
the name of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar this is a major סוגיא
Sugya in פסחים Pesachim כל מקום שנאמר לא יאכל לא תאכל לא
תאכלו kol makom she'ne'emar lo ye'achel lo tochal lo tochelu whenever the
תורה Torah says don't eat however it says it you shall not
eat it shall not be eaten you in the plural shall not
eat אחד איסור אכילה ואחד איסור הנאה במשמע. echad issur achilah ve'echad
issur hana'ah bemashma. Eat does not literally mean eat eat means any
form of benefit whether eating or physical benefit or monetary benefit it's
all included. עד שיפרט לך הכתוב כדיפרט לך בנבילה Ad she'paret lecha
hakatuv kede'paret lecha binevelah
and the way we know that eating normally means all benefit is
because there's one time where the תורה Torah says don't eat and
goes out of its way to tell you you're allowed to derive
benefit. From there we learn that normally don't eat means don't derive
benefit either because there it had to explicitly permit it. Where did
the תורה Torah go out of its way to tell you you're
allowed to derive benefit? It says don't eat a נבילה nevelah an
animal that's not שחט shechted properly give it to the גר ger
give it to the convert the sojourner give it to the non-Jew
sell it to the non-Jew that you can derive benefit the תורה's
Torah telling you don't eat it but you can get benefit from
it. Give it as a gift sell it and so on. From
there I can infer that normally when the תורה Torah says don't
eat it even means don't derive benefit because there it had to
explicitly permit it. Okay so let's read this and then I'll take
at least one or two questions. כדיפרט לך בנבילה kede'paret lecha binevelah
like
the way it made explicit it made an exception by a נבילה.
nevelah. It says לגר בנתינה lager binetinah give it to the גר
ger meaning interpret it as the convert ולאובד כוכבים במכירה ule'oved kochavim
bimechirah
or to the non-Jew sell it. דתניא De'tanya and here's where we
taught it we taught in
a ברייתא Baraita לא תאכלו כל נבילה lo tochlu kol nevelah do
not
eat any נבילה. nevelah. So that's the פסוק. pasuk. So now the
ברייתא baraisa continues. אין לי אלא לגר בנתינה ולאינו יהודי במכירה. ein
li ela lager binetina ul'aino yehudi bimchira.
I only know that you give it to the גר, ger, to
the convert, and you sell it to the non-Jew. לגר במכירה מניין?
lager bimchira minayin?
How do I know that I'm even allowed to sell it to
the convert? Now the reason is, logic is, as we are going
to see, there's a special מצוה mitzvah to be concerned for the
welfare of the גר, ger, of the convert, even the, by the
way, even the גר תושב. ger toshav. Now this is talking about,
I've actually, I should not have translated it as convert, because here
it's understood to be a convert can't eat נבלה neveilah either. גר
ger here specifically חז"ל chazal understand to be a גר תושב, ger
toshav, somebody who keeps the שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvos bnei
noach, who lives among you, but does not keep all of the
laws, and the proof being that you're giving them this נבלה neveilah
and they're eating it. Actually, there's one opinion in the rabbis that
the גר תושב ger toshav keeps all 613 laws except that they
eat נבלה. neveilah. So the תורה torah says you give them the
נבלה. neveilah. Okay, sometimes it's actually referred to as a גר אוכל
נבלה, ger ochel neveilah, okay, based on this פסוק. pasuk. So actually
it is the sojourner among you, the person living among you, but
they are living among you, they're not the stranger, they're not the
full non-Jew. So there you can give it to them. How do
I, but there you also have a מצוה mitzvah to be concerned
about the well-being and the welfare of the stranger among you. So
therefore maybe you should only give it, you shouldn't sell it because
you have to take care of them. How do I know I'm
allowed to sell it to the גר? ger? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
so it's a play on the פסוק, pasuk, לגר תתננה או מכור.
lager titnena o machor. Right, the way the פסוק pasuk reads is
to the גר ger you shall give it או o or מכור
לנכרי machor lnochri sell it to the foreigner. So by putting the
comma in a different place, we can read it לגר תתננה או
מכור. lager titnena o machor. The verbs are right next to each
other. Give it to the גר ger or sell it to him.
ולעובדי כוכבים בנתינה מניין? ul'ovdei kochavim binetina minayin?
How do I know that that's true? How do I know that
you can, the reverse, you can give it to the non-Jew? Okay,
because sometimes maybe the גמרא gemara has concerns about giving free gifts
to the non-Jews, there's those are issues sometimes that get raised. So
anyway, how do I know that that would be allowed? תלמוד לומר,
talmud lomar, so the same way by putting the comma in the
different place and by combining the
verbs, תתננה או מכור לנכרי. titnena o machor lnochri. Give it or
sell it to the non-Jew, adding, connecting the give it to the
non-Jew. נמצא אחד גר ואחד עובד כוכבים בין במכירה בין בנתינה. nimtza
echad ger v'echad oved kochavim bein bimchira bein binetina. So you can
give it or sell it whether to the convert, whether to the,
I shouldn't say convert, whether to the sojourner, whether to the stranger.
So anything you can do, it's basically telling you though this נבלה
neveilah you can get benefit from. Give it or sell it to
the non-Jew, give it or sell it to the stranger, get benefit
from it. But normally if I say don't eat, it means don't
even derive benefit. So from here you learn, one minute, don't eat
means don't even derive benefit. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei rabbi meir. That's
what רבי מאיר rabbi meir says. רבי יהודה אומר, rabbi yehuda omer,
רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda says, okay, fundamentally I agree the תורה torah
had to explicitly allow it, but I don't agree with how broadly
it's allowing it. I don't think you can equally give it or
sell it to the, to the, excuse me, to the sojourner or
to the non-Jew.
דברים ככתבם. dvarim kichtavam. It has to be the way the תורה
torah is explicit. Don't do this play read of the פסוק. pasuk.
לגר בנתינה, lager binetina, you either give it to the sojourner ולעובדי
כוכבים במכירה ul'ovdei kochavim bimchira or sell it to the foreigner, but
you can, but don't switch it. So the גמרא gemara says מאי
טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai ta'ama d'rabbi yehuda? What's רבי יהודה's rabbi yehuda
logic? אי סלקא דעתך כדאמר רבי מאיר, ei salka da'atach k'd'amar rabbi
meir, if it's like what רבי מאיר rabbi meir says that you
can do either for either, לכתוב רחמנא, lichtov rachmana, so then let
the תורה torah be more
explicit, לא תאכלו כל נבלה לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה ומכור, lo
sochelu kol neveilah lager asher bisharecha titnena v'achala umachor, and sell. או
למה לי? o lama li? Why does it say or sell it
to the stranger? שמע מינה דברים ככתבם, shma mina dvarim kichtavam, to
tell you these are two separate things. Give it to the גר,
ger, sell it to the stranger, the או o separates it. Okay,
so that's what רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda says. It's one or the,
it's only that you can't reverse it, meaning, and the logic being
that if you're going to, that the גר ger you have a
particular obligation to be concerned about the welfare, so you should give
it, you shouldn't sell it. And the non-Jew, maybe again, the גמרא
gemara isn't explicit about this, but other times we see the גמרא
gemara is concerned about just giving gifts to non-Jews, so without getting
into the details of that, and maybe therefore you shouldn't give it
as a gift, you should only sell it to the non-Jew. Okay,
so the גמרא gemara says,
that's רבי יהודה. rabbi yehuda. So רבי מאיר
אמר לך, rabbi meir amar lach, what would רבי מאיר rabbi meir
say back? האי או, hai o, why does it say או? o?
Not just say it's either or, either give to the גר ger
or sell to the non-Jew, but it is to tell you that
there's a priority. להקדים נתינה דגר למכירה דעובד כוכבים, l'hakdim netina d'ger
l'michira d'oved kochavim, to tell you that it's not all the same,
you have a permission to do it all, but if you have
to choose, better to give to the גר ger rather than to
sell to the non-Jew, even though selling to the non-Jew you'll put
some money in your pocket, because you have an obligation to concern
yourself for the welfare. welfare of the גר, ger, of the sojourner,
the stranger in your midst, so therefore that should take precedence over
selling it to the non-Jew. So permission you're allowed to do anything,
but in terms of priorities you should prioritize giving it to the
גר. ger.
ורבי יהודה, veRabbi Yehuda, what would רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say back?
להקדים נתינה דגר למכירה דעובד כוכבים, lehakdim netina deger lemechira deoved kochavim,
which was just about priorities, לא צריך קרא, lo tzarich kra, you
don't even need a verse. סברא הוא, sevara hu, there's a you
know it logically. זה אתה מצווה להחיותו וזה אי אתה מצווה להחיותו,
ze ata metzuva lehachayoto veze i ata metzuva lehachayoto, what I've been
telling you up until now. You have a מצוה mitzvah to sustain
the life of the sojourner among you, you don't have the same
type of מצוה mitzvah to be oh concern yourself with the welfare
of the foreigner, it's only the welfare of the stranger who lives
among you, and therefore obviously you know when it comes to priority,
that comes before taking care of the גר. ger. The stranger among
you comes before taking care or even selling it to the foreigner.
So the פסוק pasuk doesn't need to prioritize, and therefore what the
פסוק pasuk is actually saying is only this, only that, you cannot
cross over. Whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no no no, you're
allowed to do whatever you want, but there is an issue of
priority. Now the upshot of all of that is, whatever exactly the
priorities or the options are by נבלה, neveila, everybody agrees that don't
don't eat means don't even derive benefit unless it were not that
the פסוק pasuk went out of its way and spelled out that
that what you're allowed to do. We typeset according to רבי Rabbi
that we assume that לא תאכל lo tochal means don't derive benefit
until the פסוק pasuk tells you oh no, but here you're allowed
to derive benefit. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, only sell to
a to the to the stranger and give to the sojourner. According
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you can do everything but the but
without the פסוק pasuk having said a permission, לא תאכל lo tochal
would have meant don't only don't eat but don't derive benefit. And
there רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu learns his principle that לא תאכל lo
tochal unless the תורה Torah clearly allows it, every time the תורה
Torah says don't eat, it also means don't derive benefit. Now there's
a major סוגיא sugya in פסחים, Pesachim, where of course most of
the things the תורה Torah says don't eat, you're allowed to derive
benefit. חזיר chazir and you know the dozen things you can imagine.
So the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim goes through every single one
of them and shows you how according to רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
we can learn from a פסוק pasuk that you're allowed to derive
benefit. So there's basically winds up being more exceptions than there are
to the rule than there are you know applications of the rule.
But nevertheless in principle לא תאכל lo tochal means don't derive benefit,
and therefore by בשר בחלב basar bechalav we're going to leave it
at that and say don't derive benefit. So the purpose for us,
I want to say something else about the the נבלה neveila issue
and then I'll take the question. But for us the upshot is
how do you know you can't eat בשר בחלב? basar bechalav? Because
it's a תועבה, toeva, because the תורה Torah says don't do it,
don't do it, the product is considered a תועבה. toeva. And how
do you know you can't derive benefit? Because לא תאכל lo tochal
also means don't derive benefit. Are there two dozen exceptions to that
rule? Yes, but this isn't an exception to that rule, and here
לא תאכל lo tochal means the standard you know thing even if
it's usually there's usually an exception, here it does mean don't derive
benefit. Now one final thing and then I'll take the question. תוספות
Tosafot makes an important point. תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean
you can't sell it, you have to first give it to the
גר ger before you sell it to the non-Jew? I mean if
I've got something to sell, right, I'm in the business of you
know selling I don't know cars or whatever I'm in the business
of selling potatoes, do I have to give them to the גר
ger before I sell them? I mean I'm allowed to make a
פרנסה, parnasa, I'm allowed to sell them and make money. You know
I also have a מצוה mitzvah להחיות lehachyot my fellow Jew. So
do I have to give all of my food to my fellow
Jew rather than selling it and make money? So תוספות Tosafot says
no. תוספות Tosafot says we're assuming here this probably is like the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, like a נבלה neveila is like
a carcass. So basically you know it's not something that you're planning
on eating as meat and you didn't do the שחיטה shechita correctly.
Sort of the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is the animal
just died on you, it's a carcass. So what you're going to
get from selling it is relatively trivial. So therefore if you're only
going to get you know some trivial sum for it, better to
give it as a gift to the non- to the גר, ger,
to the sojourner and help sustain their life rather than make a
few measly bucks by selling it. Okay? So that's like a special
case. But if you look at the end of this תוספות, Tosafot,
at the תוספות Tosafot אד, ad, like three lines before the words
כדרך, kederech, תוספות Tosafot says like this, like before four three lines
directly over the words כדרך, kederech, תוספות Tosafot says
אבל פשיטא שאם יש חפץ לאדם למכור קודם ימכרנו לעובד כוכבים משיתננו
אפילו לישראל חבירו, aval pshita she'im yesh chefetz leadam limkor kodem yimkrenu
leoved kochavim misheyitnenu afilu leyisrael chaveiro, that if you try to sell
and make money you can sell to whoever wants to buy, you
don't have to give it away to the to the גר ger
or to the Jew. So here we're talking about a special case
where it was like the money you would make would be trivial,
and if it's only going to be trivial, better to give it
to somebody who can really derive serious benefit from it rather than
making a few measly bucks by selling it in the open market.
Okay? So if you've got I mean here would be the analogy,
you've got all of these used clothes and you could donate it
to a homeless shelter and you know three dozen people could have
nice clothes to keep them warm and instead you decide
you a lesson, not an exception. The question is, if that's
true, say the same about בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. If שבת Shabbos
the product is permissible, how much more so by בשר בחלב? basar
bechalav? So Rashi asks this question and Rashi's basic answer is the
following. Rashi's answer is okay, on the one hand you're right, but
on another hand there is the פסוק posuk of כל תועבה kol
toeva so it has to be talking about something and of all
the things it makes the most sense
that
he's talking about בשר בחלב basar bechalav because by these other things
the product is really somewhat incidental to the prohibition. Meaning, it's certainly
true about
threshing with a horse and a donkey together or you know, muzzling
your cow when you thresh with it. It's not like the muzzling
produced the
crushed grain. It's not like the even the cow and the donkey
together, it's not somehow like the prohibition itself was directly produced the
product, right, directly produced the איסור. issur. By בשר בחלב basar bechalav
the whole prohibition is combining the two. So there it really seems
like the that
it's the most appropriate to call the product the product of the
עבירה aveira because the whole nature of the עבירה aveira was to
bring the two together, so this is really the product of the
עבירה. aveira. That's the way Rashi explains it, and another you know
way to also maybe even more conceptualize it is going back to
the point I raised yesterday, right, remember maybe this morning where you
start by the prohibition or you start by or you know or
maybe that's not so good because we clearly are starting by the
prohibition calling it the product, but nevertheless even when you start by
the prohibition, cooking בשר בחלב basar bechalav together. I actually discussed this
when we were doing the whole issue about אפשר לסוחטו. efshar lesochto.
Is it... that was on the tape if people listen. Is the
prohibition of בשר בחלב basar bechalav the act of having cooked them
together or is the prohibition of בשר בחלב basar bechalav having commingled
the tastes through the cooking. The more you say it's about producing
this commingling of tastes through the cooking, so if that's the actual
prohibition of cooking them together is to cause the commingling of tastes
clearly the תורה Torah is concerned with the fact that you've produced
this mixture of tastes, this hybrid taste. If that's what the תורה
Torah is concerned about, that makes sense to call the product of
the עבירה aveira because that was the whole nature of the עבירה.
aveira. Okay, whereas opposed to cooking on שבת. Shabbos. You know what?
I happen to have cooked this meat on שבת, Shabbos, but I
could have cooked it on Tuesday. So the fact that I have
cooked meat is not somehow an embodiment of חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos,
right? Cooked בשר בחלב basar bechalav is an embodiment of the עבירה.
aveira. You don't get cooked בשר בחלב basar bechalav without having brought
those two together. But everything else, crushed grain, cooked meat is not
an embodiment of the איסור issur and therefore does not deserve to
be called כל שתיעבתי לך. kol sheteiafti lach. That's the sort of
elaboration on what Rashi says and that's why it doesn't make sense
to focus on בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. Yes.
So and then something that would be more comparable might be things
that result in כלאים. kilayim.
Exactly, which is the next question of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
let's take a look at the next line of the גמרא. Gemara.
So you are my perfect straight man, perfect segue. So the גמרא
Gemara says okay,
so כלאי זרעים ליסרו? kilay zerayim lissru? How about so even though
it sort of took off the table these other stuff which are
not really the direct sort of embodiment or product of the עבירה,
aveira, how about the mixing of seeds, the tangelo, the wheat and
the barley? Right, if it's not כלאי זרעים, kilay zerayim, if it's
not כלאי הכרם, kilay hakerem, if it's not with grape, the product
is actually permissible in benefit. שתיעבתי לך sheteiafti lach הוא, hu,
because that's something that I made abominable and that really is a
product of an עבירה, aveira, an embodiment of an עבירה. aveira. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, דגלי רחמנא גבי כלאי הכרם, degali rachmana
gabei kilay hakerem, since the תורה Torah says that only by when
it's a mixture with the vine, פן תקדש, pen tikdash, lest it
becomes holy is what the verse says, and the דרשה drasha is
the following:
פן תוקד אש, pen tukad esh, that's the play on words, lest
it be burnt in a fire. תקדש tikdash holy, תוקד אש tukad
esh burnt in a fire which means it deserves to be burnt,
you can't derive benefit from it. So it says that by כלאי
הכרם kilay hakerem you can't derive benefit. There the product is off
limits, הקדש, hekdesh, תוקד אש, tukad esh, אסור. assur.
מכלל דכלאי זרעים שרו. michlal dekilay zerayim sharu. From there I can
infer that normal mixed seeds are permissible. So actually here the גמרא
Gemara is saying in principle you're right. I mean what is בשר
בחלב basar bechalav if it's not a type of a כלאים? kilayim?
If it's not a type of a forbidden mixture. So the גמרא
Gemara is saying okay logically you're right, that should have been the
same, but from the fact the תורה Torah only forbids it by
כלאי כרם kilay kerem we can infer that this the תורה Torah
did allow. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא, veima, let me still
say the following: כלאי כרם אסור בין באכילה בין בהנאה, kilay kerem
assur bein baachila bein bahanaah, כלאי כרם kilay kerem you can't eat
or derive benefit, that's תוקד אש tukad esh burnt by a fire,
not even derive benefit. כלאי זרעים אכילה kilay zerayim achila
Let's at least say, okay, they're not like כלאי כרם, Kilay Kerem,
but let them still at least be somewhat forbidden. Let them at
least be forbidden in eating, even, and say that you can get,
you can derive benefit. So if it makes so much sense to
say it's forbidden by this mixture, let's even if they're not as
bad as כלאי כרם, Kilay Kerem, let's still say they're forbidden in
eating. So the גמרא Gemara says: No. היקש לכלאי בהמה. heikesh le-kilay
behema.
We know from another place it's permitted because this would have been
the next question, right? If we can't prove it by מכלאים, mi-kilayim,
I was assuming the next question if the גמרא Gemara didn't just
say that Maika would have said it, what about the mule, right?
How can you use a mule? That's a prohibition, it's again a
mixture, it's an embodiment of the עבירה. aveira. So גמרא Gemara says:
No, we already know that's permitted. How do you know that's permitted?
דכתיב, de-chtiv, the פסוק pasuk says: בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים, behemtecha lo
tarbi'a kilayim, do not crossbreed your animals, ושדך לא תזרע כלאים, u-sadecha
lo tizra kilayim, and do not crossbreed the grains in your field.
So מה בהמתך היוצא ממנו מותר, ma behemtecha ha-yotzei mimenu muttar, the
same way the product of a cross-bred animal is permissible, אף שדך
היוצא ממנו מותר, af sadecha ha-yotzei mimenu muttar, even by cross-bred seeds.
So how do we know כלאי כרם kilay kerem is permissible? Because
we know cross-bred animals. But now the question is: How do you
know cross-bred animals? ובכלאי בהמה גופא מנלן? u-ve-kilay behema gufa minalan? How
do you know cross-bred animals are
permitted? מדאסר רחמנא כלאים לגבוה מכלל דלהדיוט שרי. mi-de-asar rachmana kilayim le-gavoha
mi-chlal de-le-hediot shari. Since we know from another verse that you can't
use a cross-bred animal for קרבן, korban, right? You know, if you
cross-breed let's say a sheep and a goat, you can't bring it
as a קרבן korban even קרבנות korbanot that you're allowed to bring
either sheep or goats. So from there we can infer that it's
only forbidden as a קרבן. korban. That means that for non-קרבן korban
purposes, it is okay. So basically what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is like this: It's actually nice, it's saying some things are not
even in the category. They're not really products of an עבירה. aveira.
They're not really an embodiment of an עבירה. aveira. They're like a,
what is it, an incidental product, but they're not the, you know,
they're not the real essence of the עבירה. aveira. Those go without
saying. That's like מעשה שבת ma'aseh shabbat and other types, חורש בשור
ובחמור. choresh be-shor u-va-chamor. Other things, particularly things that are כלאים, kilayim,
are a real product and embodiment of an עבירה. aveira. There it
should be forbidden. But it just so happens that we learn out
from other verses there are a lot of exceptions. Cross-bred animals are
not a problem, cross-bred seeds are not a problem. What is a
problem is cross-bred with vine, and בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav. Those are
going to be the problem. Okay. גמרא Gemara is going to still
try to have other types of counter-proofs. So let's keep on
going. אותו ואת בנו ליתסר? oto ve-et beno leitasar? How about here's
another cross thing, cross-bred, right? What we just discussed earlier today, right?
The שחיטה shechita of a mother with its child. That's another type
of a thing that like doing two things, not exactly cross-breed but
whatever, two things together. Why when you שחט shachat the mother and
the child should you be able to eat the meat? Why don't
we say if you שחט-ed shachat the meat in a prohibition, the
meat should be forbidden? So the גמרא Gemara says: מדאסר רחמנא מחוסר
זמן לגבוה מכלל דלהדיוט שרי. mi-de-asar rachmana mechusar zeman le-gavoha mi-chlal de-le-hediot
shari. No, there I can say the same type of argument. Since
the תורה Torah says, remember if you remember when we learned the
פרק אותו ואת בנו, perek oto ve-et beno, it said that if
I שחט-ed shachat the mother today, remember that all that משנה mishnah
which spoke about what happens if they're both קרבנות korbanot and I
שחט shachat one inside and one outside. Anyway, the פסול psul of
it was if I שחט-ed shachat the mother today, the child can't
be brought as a קרבן. korban. It's מחוסר זמן mechusar zeman because
today is not a day that it can be slaughtered. So the
גמרא Gemara is saying since this concept of מחוסר זמן mechusar zeman
is a concept by קרבן, korban, from that I can infer that
if I were to do it and it wasn't a קרבן, korban,
it would be permitted. Now that seems to be a little bit
a little hard argument to understand because מחוסר זמן mechusar zeman applies
not only to אותו ואת בנו. oto ve-et beno. The classic application
is an animal less than eight days old. So okay, I know
there are some מחוסר זמן mechusar zeman that it's only a problem
as a קרבן, korban, but it doesn't prove to me אותו ואת
בנו oto ve-et beno isn't also a problem just because it also
happens to be מחוסר זמן. mechusar zeman. It's not clear how I
know that it's limited to a קרבן korban problem and not also
a problem for normal lay purposes. But that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. Now תוספות Tosafot actually says that the גמרא Gemara here could
have given the answer it gave before, the better answer, which is
slaughtering a mother and a child on the same day, it's not
an embodiment of the עבירה. aveira. Again, the fact that you have
a slaughtered calf here is not like, you know, it's incidental. I
could have slaughtered the calf on a different day. There's nothing about
a slaughtered calf that says עבירה. aveira. There's something about בשר בחלב
basar be-chalav cooked together that says עבירה. aveira. There's something about a
cross-bred animals or cross-bred, you know, things that the whole thing is
an embodiment of the עבירה. aveira. Here it's much more incidental. So
תוספות Tosafot says yeah, the גמרא Gemara could have said that answer
but it gave this answer because it was an easier answer. Okay?
So that's how you deal with the issue of אותו ואת בנו.
oto ve-et beno. Let's try again. שילוח הקן ליתסר. shiluach ha-ken leitasar.
So how about when you're supposed to send away the mother bird?
Now here it's actually quite interesting. What עבירה aveira did you do?
Why should you send away the mother bird? So רש"י Rashi says
the עבירה aveira is you didn't listen to the תורה, Torah, you
took the eggs and you took the mother bird, and now you're
supposed to send away the mother bird. But, but, you know, רש"י
Rashi is still bothered, it's not
the
product of an
עבירה. aveira. You didn't do any עבירה aveirah at all. The תורה
Torah just says send away the mother bird. But remember the verse
we're learning it from is כל שתיעבתי לך, kol she-ti'avti lach,
something that I have made abominable to you. We have been assuming
that what it means to be abominable is the product or embodiment
of an עבירה. aveirah. תוספות Tosafot says there's another way that it
could be abominable. The תורה Torah says don't don't don't take it.
If it's telling you send away the mother, it's telling you I
don't want you to take the mother. It's off limits. So if
it's telling you it's off limits, if you went and שחט shachted
it, it should remain off limits, it should remain forbidden. So the
idea of תיעבתי ti'avti doesn't have to be defined only as the
product of an עבירה, aveirah, it could also be defined as another
way in which it is indicated as being off limits. So why
don't I say that if you שחט shachted the mother bird, the
תורה Torah made it off limits, it should remain off limits. Let's
see the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לא אמרה תורה
שלח לתקלה. lo amrah Torah shalach l'takalah. You send away the bird,
I sent it away, a week later Charlie you're going to catch
it. So if the תורה Torah had made it off limits, then
anybody who caught that bird would be eating a forbidden object and
the תורה Torah obviously would not have allowed that. So yes it's
true the תורה's Torah told me send it away, but it would
not ever have wanted the result of that to be that the
bird is now forbidden, that would not have been fair to everybody
else. Okay, so that is how we know that that would not
include. So that was a fascinating discussion about the conceptual idea, meaning
even if what's the basis for the prohibition or not, here is
us talking really getting to this concept and this is what I've
been talking about about the relationship of the איסור אכילה issur achilah
and the איסור בישול, issur bishul, does it focus on not cooking
and then בישול bishul is just a byproduct, excuse me eating is
a byproduct of not cooking, and that's certainly or the reverse, it
focuses on not eating and בישול bishul is a safeguard. Here it
certainly seems like it's the former. We basically don't want you to
cook. If you've cooked, there are then the product of that is
an embodiment of the what you've done that was so wrong, that
has to be forbidden as well. Do we always say that? No,
most of the time we don't say that. But some things that
we really don't want you that we really are opposed to, like
כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem and you know maybe that was even another
case, but okay, everything else was an exception, but at least some
things if it's an embodiment of the forbidden act, it's going to
remain forbidden as well. Okay, so that's one way of learning it
out, but it points at a very particular understanding of the nature
of בשר בחלב basar b'chalav and the relationship of cooking to eating.
Yes, Mike?
תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah would also be like
הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah?
No,
הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No,
הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah? No, הנאה?
hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah? No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah?
No, הנאה? hana'ah? Okay, so the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says that is
one learning, that it's the product of an
עבירה aveirah *aveirah*, and the עיקר ikkar, *ikkar* is to the חוקק
*chokek*. אמר ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Amar Reish Lakish*, said ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish.
*Reish
Lakish*, מנין לבשר בחלב שאסר *minayin le'basar b'chalav she'asar*?
How do we know, here's another approach, how do we know it's
forbidden? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar* by פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, אל תאכלו ממנו
נא ובשל מבשל *al tochlu mimenu na u'vashel mevushal*. Don't eat the
קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach* raw or cooked in water. שאין תלמוד
לומר מבשל *She'ein Talmud lomar mevushal*. Why did it have to say
ובשל מבשל *u'vashel mevushal*, a double language of
cooked? Why didn't it just say
don't eat from it בשל *bashel*? So מה
תלמוד לומר מבשל *ma Talmud lomar mevushal*, what's the point of the
extra word of מבשל *mevushal*, cooked, by קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*?
לומר לך *Lomar lecha*, to say to you, יש לך בשול אחר
שהוא כזה *yesh lecha bishul acher she'hu kazeh*.
Not only can the קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach* unite, be בשל
*bashel*, but there's something else that's מבשל *mevushal* that you also can't
eat. What is it? What other thing does the תורה Torah *Torah*
care about if it's cooked? בשר בחלב basar bechalav *Basar b'chalav*. So
ואיזה זה *v'eizeh zeh*, what is it? ואיזה זה בשר בחלב basar
bechalav *v'eizeh zeh basar b'chalav*. That's something else that is cooked. So
we learn it out from קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* and presumably from
there we'll also learn out an איסור הנאה isur hana'ah, *issur hana'ah*
because לא תאכל lo tachal *lo tochal* will also mean איסור הנאה
isur hana'ah? *issur hana'ah*.
אל תאכלו ממנו נא
ובשל מבשל *Al tochlu mimenu na u'vashel mevushal*, the double language of
בישול bishul. *bishul*, don't eat a קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* cooked and
don't eat something else that's cooked together that's not supposed to be
cooked together. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Amar lei
Rabbi Yochanan*, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* said to ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*, כעורה זו ששנה רבי rebbi. *ke'urah zu
she'shana Rabbi*? What, is it disgusting to you what רבי rebbi, *Rabbi*
taught? Meaning why you, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*, are you
making up new דרשות drashot *drashos*? רבי rebbi *Rabbi*, רבי rebbi. יהודה
הנשיא *Rabbi Yehudah HaNasi*, already had a דרשה drasha *drasha* to learn
this that way. Why don't you like it? Here's what he taught.
לא תאכלנו lo tochlenu, *Lo tochlenu*, בבשר בחלב הכתוב מדבר *be'basar b'chalav
hakatuv medaber*, you shall not eat it. Okay, so this is, now
this is talking about an animal that was a קרבן *korban* that
became invalid and the תורה Torah *Torah* says you should, you know,
you can slaughter it in your gate, בשעריך תאכלנו הטמא והטהור יחדיו
כצבי וכאיל *bish'arecha tochlenu hatamei v'hatahor yachdav katzvi u'cha'ayal*, what, the hart
and the deer, you can eat it, you know, רק את דמו
לא תאכלו על הארץ תשפכנו כמים *rak es damo lo tochlu al
ha'aretz tishpechenu kamayim*, לא תאכלנו *lo tochlenu*, do not eat it, meaning
the blood, למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים *lema'an yitav lecha v'ha'arachta yamim*
etc. So it says, after it says don't eat the blood, eat
these animals that were קרבנות *korbanos* that were redeemed, but don't eat
the blood, it repeats don't eat it. Why does it have to
say don't eat it after it just said don't eat it? So
לא תאכלנו *lo tochlenu*, בבשר בחלב הכתוב מדבר *be'basar b'chalav hakatuv medaber*,
of course it doesn't just mean blood here, it means don't eat
meat and milk. Okay, אתה אומר בבשר בחלב הכתוב מדבר *atah omer
be'basar b'chalav hakatuv medaber*, you say it's talking about meat or milk,
או אינו אלא באחד מכל איסורין שבתורה *o eino ela be'achad mikol
issurin she'baTorah*? Maybe it means some other thing in the תורה Torah?
*Torah*? How do you know it's talking about meat or milk? אמרת
צא ולמד *Amarta tzei u'lmad*, go and learn. מה בי"ג מדות שהתורה
נדרשת בהם *mah b'yud gimmel middos she'haTorah nidreshes bahem*, thirteen ways the
תורה Torah *Torah* is interpreted, one of them is דבר הלמד מענינו
*davar halamed me'inyano*, ודבר הלמד מסופו *v'davar halamed mesofo* etc. So something
that can be learned out from context. So לא תאכלנו *lo tochlenu*
we'll learn from the context is בשר בחלב basar bechalav, *basar b'chalav*.
Now where do you get the context of בשר בחלב basar bechalav.
*basar b'chalav* in a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that's talking about blood and
about animals that were קרבנות *korbanos* that were redeemed? So במה הכתוב
מדבר בשני מינין *bameh hakatuv medaber? Bishnei minin*. It's talking about two
things. What are the two things? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the
two things is the צבי *tzvi* and the איל *ayal*, the same
way you would eat the צבי *tzvi* and the איל *ayal*, two
separate things, although צבי *tzvi* and איל *ayal* are both interpreted, I
don't know, there's some type of a deer and a hart and
anyway whatever they are. רש"י *Rashi* says the שני מינין *shnei minin*
are that this is an animal that was a קרבן *korban* and
now has been redeemed and is now חולין *chullin*. And this animal
has aspects of קרבן *korban* to it, limits of it that are
remnants of its קרבן *korban* status, and aspects of חולין *chullin* to
it. So there's some sense of a hybrid going on here. So
since there's some degree of a hybrid going on here, so אף
כאן בשני מינין *af kan bishnei minin*, if the תורה Torah *Torah*
says don't eat it means some other hybrid don't eat. What's the
other hybrid? Don't eat בשר בחלב basar bechalav *basar b'chalav*. Of course
this hybrid you can eat, you just can't eat the blood, but
don't eat a different hybrid, don't eat בשר בחלב basar bechalav *basar
b'chalav*. ואי מההיא *V'ee mehahi*, so why did רבי *Rabbi* so he
says to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*, what's the matter with
רבי's *Rabbi's* דרשה drasha. *drasha*? Now of all the דרשות *drashos*, רבי's
*Rabbi's* does seem the most far-fetched. I mean if you're learning it
out from קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* you might as well learn it
out from פסולי המוקדשין *pesulei hamukdashin*. But okay maybe that's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying to him, if you're learning
it out from קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, why don't you learn it
after רבי's *Rabbi's* דרשה *drasha* by פסולי המוקדשין *pesulei hamukdashin*? So he
says ואי מההיא *v'ee mehahi*, if it was from that, הוה אמינא
*hava amina*, I would have said הני מילי באכילה אבל בהנאה b'hana'ah.
לא *hani mili ba'achilah aval b'hana'ah lo*. Maybe it's only forbidding eating,
right, because the same way blood, you only cannot eat blood but
you can derive benefit. So maybe here too if it's learned from
the same פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, maybe you could derive benefit. But when
it talks about the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, if you cook the
קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* you not only can you not eat it,
you can't derive benefit, a קרבן *korban* that has not been, you
know, that's not a proper fit to be eaten because of its
קדושה kedushah *kedusha* status you can't even derive benefit. So why did
I go to קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* rather than here? Because the
model of קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* tells me no benefit when קרבן
פסח *Korban Pesach* was done incorrectly. The model of blood just tells
me no eating, but benefit would have been a possibility. ורבי בהנאה
מנא ליה *V'Rabbi b'hana'ah mna lei*? And where would רבי *Rabbi* learn
הנאה hana'ah? *hana'ah*? נפקא ליה מהכא *Nafka lei mehacha*. He would learn
it from here. נאמר כאן *Ne'emar kan*, it says here, כי עם
קדוש אתה ki am kadosh atah, לה' אלוהיך *ki am kadosh atah
l'Hashem Elokecha*. Okay, that's what it says by, what do you call
it, by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* by בשר בחלב basar bechalav *basar
b'chalav*, right? It says כי עם קדוש kadosh. אתה לה' אלוהיך *ki
am kadosh atah l'Hashem Elokecha*. Is that the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* by
בשר בחלב basar bechalav *basar b'chalav*? דברים י"ד *Devarim yud daled*. Yeah,
yeah. It says, where is it? כי עם קדוש kadosh, אתה לה'
אלוקיך ובך בחר ה' להיות לו לעם סגולה מכל העמים אשר על
פני האדמה, לא תאכל lo tochal, כל תועבה. Wait, where is it?
Where's the? That's at the beginning of all the forbidden animals. Oh,
and at the very end it says, it says כי עם קדוש
אתה לה' אלוקיך לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. ki am kadosh atah
l'Hashem Elokecha lo tvashel gdi bachalav imo. So there it says קדוש.
kadosh. ונאמר להלן, v'ne'emar l'halan, and if we're talking about קדוש, kadosh,
it says over there by a totally different context, ולא יהיה קדש
בבני ישראל, v'lo yihyeh kadesh bivnei Yisrael, that there should be no
male prostitute among the children of Israel. מה להלן בהנאה, mah l'halan
b'hana'ah, there we're talking about sexual pleasure, so it's pleasure but it's
not eating pleasure, and that's what's forbidden is pleasure beyond eating, אף
כאן בהנאה, af kan b'hana'ah, here too what's forbidden is pleasure, not
just eating but all types of pleasure. So we learn it out
from the קדוש. kadosh Of course, once we're learning it out from
the קדוש, it's not clear why we also needed the extra פסוק
pasuk about eating, but maybe that's to tell you that they're separate
prohibitions. One prohibition of eating and one prohibition of deriving benefit. Question?
Yes. But there are other things where we have a prohibition that
comes right after קדוש and we don't prohibit הנאה? hana'ah, Yeah, it
is very clear, if it wasn't already clear without me saying this,
that the תנא tanna started with a מסורה mesorah that בשר בחלב
basar bechalav. was אסור באכילה asur b'achilah and אסור בהנאה, asur b'hana'ah,
and they worked backwards to figure it out. I mean, in general,
that's a question that scholars ask and that the ראשונים rishonim ask,
which is, when you have דרשות in the גמרא, gemara how much
do we assume that they did not know what the הלכה halacha
is and they said, let's look at the פסוקים psukim and use
our different methodologies and figure out what the הלכה halacha is, or
how much did they have a מסורה mesorah what the הלכה halacha
is and say, let's figure out where this comes from the פסוקים.
psukim. So the obvious, the basic point by any question like this
is that יש ויש, yesh v'yesh, sometimes it's one, sometimes it's another,
sometimes it's clear that they're starting with the פסוקים psukim and sometimes
it's clear that they start with knowing the bottom line and they're
working backwards. But different scholars will differ, contemporary academics will differ about
that, but the ראשונים rishonim also differed with it. For example, the
רמב"ן Ramban says, right, just to digress for a second, the גמרא
gemara says you can't learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah unless you
have a מסורה mesorah from your רבי. Okay, so the רמב"ן Ramban
says, if that's true, how do you explain all these גמרות gemarot
that say, well, why did you learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
this way, you should have learned the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah that
way, and why not learn it this way? What do you mean?
You need a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, you need a מסורה mesorah
from your רבי, so what
are you bothering me why didn't I learn it this way? This
is my tradition. So the רמב"ן Ramban says no, all that means
is that from your
רבי you have a מסורה mesorah that this is the הלכה halacha
and אפשר ללמוד דבר זה בגזירה שוה. efshar lilmod davar zeh b'gezeirah
shavah. Okay, so you have the tradition about what the bottom line
is and you're told that you can figure it out through גזירה
שוה. gezeirah shavah. Then you can figure out yourself how to do
the גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, so the גמרא gemara can challenge how
are you doing your גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Anyway, the point is
that very sometimes we start from the end and we work backwards.
It seems clear that that's what's going on here. So why is
it that here the גמרא Gemara is saying לא תאכל lo tochal,
means איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah why is it learning out from קדש
kadesh איסור הנאה? issur hana'ah, Because we know that בשר בחלב basar
bechalav. is אסור בהנאה. asur b'hana'ah. That seems to be the basic
answer, so we're working backwards. Although we will find a dissenting opinion
coming up. Okay. Yes, very interesting, I find it very sharp with
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. given his history with the רבי. Very barbed
comments. And this is of a piece with the מעשה ma'aseh where
it ultimately led to רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's death. This is where
he told him, you know, you're a thief, you know thievery. Oh
right, not this comment of כורא דשושנא רבי, kura d'shushna rebbi, but
right, right, but of a piece that it seems that there was
this, yeah, they were these barbed comments that kept coming from רבי
יוחנן to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Yeah, I think it sometimes comes
in the opposite direction also. I think that their whole, I can't
remember offhand, but I mean. Well, then רבי יוחנן said. Yeah, when
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish died, every time I said something he would
raise. Yeah, I mean, I think it was like, I think it
was a type of a מלחמה לשם שמים, milchama l'shem shamayim, but
right, but yeah, definitely, yeah, I definitely agree with the characterization. Shai
Frohlich has recently published two volumes on מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוחנן
and ריש לקיש. Oh yeah? Interesting. Yeah. Okay. So alright, so תוספות
by the way says we needed the פסוק about אכילה achilah not
just הנאה, hana'ah, so I shouldn't think that it's just talking about
הנאה, hana'ah to know, maybe it's talking about הנאה hana'ah. that isn't
אכילה, achilah, it's ממש mamash like the case of קדש. kadesh. No,
no, no, אכילה achilah plus הנאה. hana'a. Okay, anyway, that's רבי'ס Rebbi's
learning out from two very unlikely sources, the male prostitute and what
was it, and פסולי מוקדשים. psulei mukdashim. Alright. דבי רבי אליעזר תנא,
Dvei Rabbi Eliezer tana, here's another approach. דבי רבי אליעזר Dvei Rabbi
Eliezer taught, לא תאכלו כל נבלה, lo tochlu kol neveilah, don't eat
any נבלה, neveilah, and the end of that פסוק is, right, is
בשר בחלב, basar bechalav right? לא תאכלו כל נבלה לגר אשר בשעריך
תתננה ואכלה או מכור לנכרי כי עם קדוש אתה לה' אלוקיך לא
תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. lo tochlu kol neveilah lager asher bish'arecha titnenah
v'achalah o machor l'nochri ki am kadosh atah l'Hashem Elokecha lo tvashel
gdi bachalav imo. Okay, so don't eat נבלה neveilah ending with בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav אמר תורה כשתמכרנה לא תבשלנה ותמכרנה. amar Torah k'shetimkrenah
lo tvashlenah v'timkrenah. So what does it say you do with this
נבלה? neveilah? Give it to the stranger or sell
to the stranger, give it to the sojourner. So what does it
say you do with this נבלה? neveilah? Give it to the stranger
or sell to the stranger, give it to the sojourner, and then
it says don't cook it in meat and milk. So meaning give
it to them but don't cook it first and then give it
to them. Why? Because if you cooked it first you wouldn't be
allowed to give it to them because it would be אסור בהנאה.
assur behana'ah. Okay, so that's cute. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא,
Debei
Rabbi Yishmael tana, the house of Rabbi Yishmael taught, לא תבשל גדי
בחלב אמו, lo tevashel g'di bachalav imo, ג' פעמים.
gimel pe'amim. Finally, somebody learned Rashi! Okay, this is great. אחד לאיסור
אכילה ואחד לאיסור הנאה ואחד לאיסור בישול. Echad le'issur achilah ve'echad le'issur
hana'ah ve'echad le'issur bishul.
Three times: one
for eating, one for, one for cooking. By the way, I should
say that, I mean, I didn't
spell it all out, but I've been talking all along, what's the
relationship with the איסור בישול issur bishul to the איסור אכילה? issur
achilah? So part of that I
think, like the first approach I said,
it's about תיאספו לך, te'asefu lach, certainly emphasizes the prohibition of בישול.
Eating is just an outgrowth, a derivative of it. Other פסוקים pesukim
here have them as more independent, right? בשל מבושל, bashel mevushal, לא
תאכלנו, have it not so much as a derivative but more independent.
Another question to ask is, what's the relationship between the איסור הנאה
issur hana'ah and the איסור אכילה?
issur achilah? Are those independent, or is an extension of eating? When
the גמרא Gemara learned it about from anytime the תורה Torah says
לא תאכל, lo tochal, it includes איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah.
so is an extension of the איסור אכילה. issur achilah. When the
תורה Torah learns about the איסור הנאה hana'a. from קדש בפני ישראל,
kadesh bifnei Yisrael, okay, that clearly is something that is conceptually distinct
and separate. And there are implications להלכה lehalacha whether
you think is related to eating or not, like the question of
if you cook נבלה בחלב, neveilah bechalav, does the fact that there's
no איסור אכילה issur achilah of that
because of אין איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur,
no איסור אכילה בשר בחלב issur achilah basar bechalav also mean that
there's no איסור הנאה בשר בחלב issur hana'ah basar bechalav by the
case of the dog food, you know, נבלה בחלב? neveilah bechalav? If
is part of אכילה, achilah, then אכילה achilah didn't take effect, also
wouldn't take effect. But if is independent, then maybe אכילה achilah didn't
take effect but did. At least that's one way of learning it.
So these are all these questions: what's the relationship of cooking to
eating, and what's the relationship of benefit to eating? Are they independent,
are they related? And the דרשה of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the
last one of three times, you know, could go all ways, but
it certainly sounds a little bit like they're independent. Or you could
say they're all interdependent, I mean, because they're all learned from the
same פסוק.
Why do you need to
say it three times then? Well, but you need to know that
they're all included. But in the end, so you can go either
way with that דרשה.
Okay, so the question really is on Rashi. Why did Rashi pick
this one in the תורה?
Torah Well, first of all, it's the simplest. I mean, it's like
very numerical: one, two, three. And also it helps explain answers in
other questions. Why did the תורה Torah repeat it? So you have
two issues you have to solve: why did the תורה repeat it
three times, and how do we know you can't eat it? So
this approach is a simple answer to both questions.
What do the other פסוקים pesukim say about that?
Well, you know, we learned out גדי g'di six times and חלב
chalav six times and all these other things. And anyway, why does
the תורה tell you not to worship עבודה זרה avodah zarah two
dozen times? Not everything has an answer. Okay, anyway, going on, תניא
אידך תניא, tanya idach tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא. braita. איסי
בן יהודה אומר, Issi ben Yehuda omer, מניין לבשר שנתבשל בחלב שאסור?
minayin lebasar shenitbashel bechalav she'assur? How do you know it's forbidden? נאמר
כאן כי עם קדוש אתה, ne'emar kan ki am kadosh atah, again,
you're holy people, ונאמר להלן ואנשי קדש תהיון לי, vene'emar lehalan ve'anshei
kodesh tihyun li, be holy people to me, ובשר בשדה טרפה לא
תאכלו, uvasar basadeh tereifah lo tocheilu, don't eat an animal that's a
טרפה, tereifah, that, you know, has a puncture. So מה להלן אסור,
mah lehalan assur, the same way there the holiness and not relating
to טרפה tereifah is a holiness of not eating certain food, אף
כאן אסור. af kan assur. So here too the holiness that's said
in relationship to בשר בחלב basar bechalav. is not just a holiness
of cooking, holiness means separating from forbidden food. And that's probably not
so bad in terms of, I understand, but in terms of פשט
pshat it's not so bad. You're saying a concept of holiness, you
know, is very much used in connection with eating forbidden food, restraining
from eating certain types of food. So if the תורה is going
to use that phrase of קודש kodesh by בשר בחלב basar bechalav.
as well, maybe it carries with it not just not cooking but
also not eating. Okay, ואין לי אלא באכילה, ve'ein li ela ba'achilah,
I only know eating, בהנאה מניין, behana'ah minayin, how do I know
not to derive benefit? אמרת קל וחומר. amarta kal vachomer. Now we
thought we were free from the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, here we
have one more, which goes to the end of the דף. daf.
ומה ערלה, umah orlah, now we're back to whether an עבירה aveirah,
was done to it. By ערלה orlah you didn't do an עבירה,
aveirah, אסורה בהנאה, assurah behana'ah, you can't derive benefit. בשר בחלב שנעבדה
בו עבירה, basar bechalav shene'evdah bo aveirah, בשר בחלב basar bechalav that
you did an עבירה, aveirah אינו דין שאסור בהנאה, eino din she'assur
behana'ah, how much more so should it be אסור בהנאה? assur behana'ah?
Now there are plenty of things you do עבירה aveirah with which
are not אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, but the key the גמרא's Gemara
going to say is, yes, that's why I couldn't have just learned
it from the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But once I learn from
אנשי קודש anshei kodesh that it's אסור באכילה, assur ba'achilah, I don't
have to, some things you do עבירה aveirah to are totally permissive.
Here I already know it's אסור באכילה. assur ba'achilah. All I have
to do is take now the baby step, not the big leap,
but the baby step and add to איסור אכילה issur achilah also
איסור הנאה. hana'a. From that I can learn out from other things
where עבירות aveirot were done from this קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ערלה,
orlah, no עבירה aveirah was done for it, אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
This, an עבירה avera was done, and I already know it's אסור
באכילה, assur ba'achilah, I should be able to take the next step
and say it's also forbidden in benefit. Okay, שנעבדה בו עבירה. shene'evdah
bo aveirah. Orla was never permitted, from the moment it grew it
was forbidden, so therefore it's forbidden in benefit. So this בשר בחלב
basar bechalav was at one stage permissible until you cooked it together.
Maybe that should prevent it from becoming forbidden in benefit. So the
גמרא Gemara says חמץ בפסח יוכיח. chometz b'Pesach yochiach. No, I can
count to prove that from חמץ chometz on פסח. שהיתה לו שעת
הכושר, she-haysah lo sha'as ha-kosher, that was כשר kosher before פסח began.
ואסור בהנאה, v'assur behana'a, and now it's אסור, assur, so things can
become forbidden in benefit even if they were once permitted. So the
same is true by בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, מה לחמץ בפסח שכן ענוש כרת. ma l'chometz b'Pesach
she-ken anush kares. That's weighty, that's punishable by כרת. kares. That's not
true about בשר בחלב. basar bechalav So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
כלאי הכרם יוכיח. kil'ay hakerem yochiach. So let's go back to כלאיים,
kil'ayim, not back, let's introduce כלאי הכרם kil'ay hakerem שאינם בכרת, she-einam
b'kares, כלאיים kil'ayim of the vine does not have the punishment of
כרת, kares, ואסור בהנאה, v'assur behana'a, and is forbidden in benefit. למה
לי גזירה שוה, Lama li g'zeira shava, okay. So therefore the גמרא's
Gemara basic פשט pshat about this is I put all these three
in their cholent. Okay, ערלה orla is forbidden in benefit, כלאי הכרם
kil'ay hakerem is forbidden in benefit, בשר בחלב basar bechalav is forbidden.
So therefore it's forbidden. So if those things are forbidden in benefit,
certainly בשר בחלב basar bechalav that you did an עבירה avera should
also be forbidden in benefit. Now you're going to say those are
different. Why? ערלה orla is different that it never was permissible. חמץ
בפסח chometz b'Pesach is different that it's כרת. kares. Okay, but the
common denominator is not that it was permissible, not that it's not
by כרת, kares, because that's not shared. The common denominator is these
are things that are אסור באכילה, assur ba'achila, they're also אסור בהנאה,
assur behana'a, so certainly the same should be true about בשר בחלב.
basar bechalav. And כלאי הכרם kil'ay hakerem by the way is not
ענוש כרת, anush kares, not punishable by כרת, kares, was presumably was
permissible for a while until it started growing, and there it's אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'a, so you see that things can be not כרת,
kares, not at one stage earlier permissible and still forbidden in benefit.
So the same can be true about בשר בחלב. basar bechalav It
was permissible it's true, it's not כרת, kares, but nevertheless let it
be forbidden in benefit, certainly because an עבירה was done with it.
Okay, so let's just read a little bit more about this. I
know it's late at night to work about worry about these קל
וחומר, kal vachomers, but if we don't get through a little bit
more we'll have to worry about it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So let's take a, so the גמרא Gemara says okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says למה לי גזירה שוה? lama li g'zeira shava? ליתי
כולהו בקל וחומר מערלה. laysi kulu b'kal vachomer me'orla. So the גמרא
Gemara says why did you need to make this whole גזירה שוה
g'zeira shava of learning it out from אנשי קודש? anshei kodesh? Now
that you've learned out from ערלה, orla, כלאיים, kil'ayim, חמץ, chometz, אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'a, so learn out איסור אכילה issur achila as well
from those three things. מה ערלה שלא נעבדה בו עבירה אסורה בין
באכילה בין בהנאה, ma orla she-lo ne'evda bo avera asura bein ba'achila
bein behana'a, the same way ערלה orla no sin was done and
you can't either eat or derive benefit, בשר בחלב שנעבדה בו עבירה,
basar bechalav she-ne'evda bo avera, בשר בחלב basar bechalav you did a
sin, אין לו דין שאסור בין באכילה בין בהנאה, ein lo din
she-asur bein ba'achila bein behana'a, how much more so is it forbidden
both in eating and benefit? So the גמרא Gemara says no, if
that was the whole point that because a sin was done we're
going to prove everything is forbidden, you can't do it by that.
There are clear exceptions to that rule. There are clear sins that
sins were done to and you can eat and derive benefit. משום
דאיכא למימר, mishum d'ika l'meimar, חורש בשור וחמור וחושם פי פרה בדשה
יוכיחו, choresh b'shor v'chamor v'chosem pi para b'dasha yochichu, going back to
what we said before. When you thresh with an ox and a
donkey or you muzzle a cow, שנעבדה בהם עבירה, she-ne'evda bahen avera,
you did a sin, ושרו, v'sharu, and you can derive benefit from
their product, from the animals. So therefore this is what it says.
We're not just saying anything a sin was done from you can't
eat. We know that's not true. What we're saying is once we
can prove you can't eat בשר בחלב basar bechalav because of אנשי
קודש, anshei kodesh, so I know fundamentally it's forbidden. Now I'm going
to make a קל וחומר kal vachomer that oh if I already
know it's forbidden then certainly it should be forbidden in benefit because
you did a sin with it and other things you didn't even
do sins with are forbidden in benefit, certainly this if we already
know it's forbidden in eating should certainly be forbidden in benefit. Okay
and now the גמרא Gemara is just going to ask why we
needed to bring all three of the examples in. למה לי למימר
כלאי הכרם יוכיח? lama li l'meimar kil'ay hakerem yochiach? Why do you
have to bring in כלאיים? kil'ayim? לימא ערלה תוכיח והדר דינא וליתי
למהצד? leima orla tochiach v'hadar dina v'leysi l'mahatzad? Right why not just
say like I was telling you, the common denominator between ערלה orla
and חמץ בפסח, chometz b'Pesach, because of those two you can't emphasize
כרת kares because that's not true about ערלה, orla, you can't emphasize
it was never forbidden, it's not true about חמץ בפסח. chometz b'Pesach.
So the common denominator there should be enough, why do you have
to introduce כלאיים? kil'ayim? So אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi משום
דאיכא למימר נבלה תוכיח. mishum d'ika l'meimar neveila tochiach. No because there's
exceptions to this rule as well. There are things that are forbidden
in eating and permissible in הנאה. שאסורה באכילה מותרת בהנאה. she-asura ba'achila
muteres behana'a. What are you going to try to say? You're going
to try to say oh we're going to learn from ערלה orla
and חמץ chometz that anything forbidden in eating is forbidden in הנאה.
That's absurd. There are plenty of things that are forbidden in eating
and not forbidden in הנאה. So you can't just prove it from
those two, you had to introduce a third. Of course the question
is so what are you going to do by introducing the third?
You're still going to try to make a... הכי אמינא משמיה דריש
לקיש, hachi amina mishmei deReish Lakish, here's what we say in the
name of ריש לקיש. כל מה הצד מגופו פרכינן, Kol mah hatzad
migufo parchinan, מעלמא לא פרכינן. me'alma lo parchinan. Anytime we make an
argument of a common denominator, you can ask an internal question, not
an external question. Meaning, so you can say, "Oh, that common denominator
doesn't make sense, here's a way it's more lenient, here's a way
it's more strict." You can't say, "Oh wait, this rule doesn't work
because I know a case, an external case, in which the rule
isn't true." So you're not allowed to ask that. That's an offsides
question. Seems like a reasonable question, how could you make an argument
of a rule if it doesn't work? But no, that's an offsides
question. The basic structure of what the גמרא's Gemara, going to do
is say like this: When you had the two cases, you were
allowed to ask a question from מעלמא. me'alma. You know, grab a
counterexample from some other case. When you introduce three, then the fact
that you can have a counterexample does not undermine the rule. Okay,
there might be exceptions, there are counterexamples, exceptions exist, but something we
don't know is an exception will still assert our rule. So with
just two, we would not have been able to make the argument
because we would have said there are things that you are forbidden
in eating, you can derive benefit, like נבילה. neveilah. But once we
introduced כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem and had three to learn it from,
then we can ignore the exceptions and apply our rule to בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav, Yeah, that's always the rule. Yeah, that's always the
crack. The point is בשר בחלב basar bechalav, we don't know what
the הלכה halachah is. We know נבילה neveilah is permissible בהנאה. בשר
בחלב there's a question. אסור באכילה, Assur b'achilah, is it אסור בהנאה?
assur b'hana'ah? Yes or no? So for that we'll derive this rule
from these three cases. How do you know נבילה neveilah is the
exception? You don't, but in these three cases you're able to, you
assert a rule that anything אסור באכילה assur b'achilah is אסור בהנאה.
assur b'hana'ah. You said, you said בשר בחלב we don't know. Right,
but נבילה neveilah we know. Oh, because the תורה says, לגר אשר
בשעריך תתננה ואכלה. Lager asher bish'arecha titnenah va'achalach. So it tells us
explicitly. It's basically at the end of the day, it's not radically
different from what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu said. Anytime it says don't
eat, it means don't derive benefit, except for the six dozen exceptions.
But otherwise that's the rule. So here the point is, here the
reason we couldn't say that is you didn't have the verb don't
eat. Here how do we know you can't eat it? Because it
says קודש, kodesh, אנשי קודש. anshei kodesh. קודש kodesh means don't eat,
but it didn't have the verb don't eat. So from there we
have to say, ah, but now we know from this צד השוה
tzad hashaveh that anything you don't eat you don't derive benefit, except
for the exceptions which we're not going to pay attention to. Okay,
so anyway let's just finish that up. מעלמא לא פרכינן. Me'alma lo
parchinan. אי הכי, I hachi, כייתי במה הצד? kaysi b'mehatzad? So if
you can't, if you can't ask a question from outside, why not
just learn it from the common denominator of the first two? משום
דאיכא למיפרך, Mishum de'ika lemifrach, הצד השוה שבהן שכן גידולי קרקע. hatzad
hashaveh shebahen sheken gidulei karka. No, no, no. If you just had
learned it from פסח and כלאיים, kilayim, you would have said, "Oh,
those are different. That's because, I mean פסח and ערלה, orlah, that's
because they grow from the ground." You know, חמץ chametz comes from
wheat and ערלה orlah comes from the ground, so we would have
found a trivial reason to not make it apply to בשר בחלב.
Again, the basic point is that when you only have two, it's
easier to just dismiss. אי הכי, I hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara
if you could have dismissed it that way, השתא נמי איכא למיפרך,
hasha nami ika lemifrach, מה לכלאיים שכן גידולי קרקע? mah lekilayim sheken
gidulei karka? The same is true when you introduce כלאיים, kilayim, it
also grows from the ground, so dismiss the rule. No. So אמר
ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי, הכי אמינא משמיה דריש לקיש, amar lei
Rav Mordechai le-Rav Ashi hacha amina mishmei de-Reish Lakish, here's what we
say in the name of ריש לקיש. כל מה הצד פרכינן כל
דהו. Kol mah hatzad parchinan kol dehu. Anytime you make a common
denominator about of two, you can have a trivial question, at least
as long as it's internal, not from an external case like we
said before, and that trivial question can allow you to dismiss it.
So the question is, oh, these two grow from the ground, בשר
בחלב doesn't grow from the ground, and that would have been enough
to dismiss the rule if it was just two cases. לא אם
אמרת, Lo im amarta, when you say no, here's yet another example,
meaning when we introduce כלאיים kilayim as the third case, לא אם
אמרת lo im amarta is in quotes, לא אם אמרת lo im
amarta whatever, מקל וחומר פרכינן כל דהו, mikal vachomer parchinan kol dehu,
מקל וחומר פרכינן, mikal vachomer parchinan, כל דהו לא פרכינן. kol dehu
lo פרכינן. If you had an argument that this case is really
more lenient and those cases were more strict, a good reason to
dismiss it, we would dismiss it. But once you have a third
case, we're not going to dismiss it for a trivial reason. So
basically here's the, here is the upshot. It's a little complicated but
here's the upshot. The argument is anything forbidden in אכילה achilah is
also forbidden in benefit. We learn that out from חמץ, chametz, כלאיים,
kilayim, and ערלה. orlah. Are there exceptions like נבילה? neveilah? Yes, but
we're going to ignore exceptions. You can't ask from exceptions from outside
cases. Okay, and we're going to apply this to בשר בחלב where
we don't know. We're going to say that's the rule, אסור באכילה
assur b'achilah אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Why did you need three cases?
Because if it was only two, we could have dismissed it by
something trivial like, "Oh, they just grow from the ground. It's a
special rule for things that grow from the ground." So when you
have three, even though all three of them grow from the ground,
now you have to have a good reason to dismiss it, and
since we don't have a good reason, from this we're going to
learn that anything forbidden in אכילה. achilah. forbidding in benefit unless you
know that it's an exception to the rule. Like Rabbi Abahu's rule,
except for Rabbi Abahu was based on a verse of לא תאכל,
the verb of not eating, and this is because we know you
can't eat it from the word of אנשי קודש, anshei kodesh, and
therefore we need this other rule to say don't derive benefit. Okay,
ולפרוך לכולהו מכולהו שכן גידולי קרקע. velifroch lekulu malkula sheken gidulei karka.
The גמרא sort of re-asks the same question. Why don't you just
say they all grow from the ground? I think she's already answered
that, so we'll just read this answer and be done with it.
אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי Amar leh Rav Mordechai l'Rav Ashi,
הכי אמינא משמיה דריש לקיש, hachi amina mishmei deReish Lakish, again, here's
what we say in the name of ריש לקיש. ריש לקיש has
a lot of play in this דף. daf. חדא מחדא מקולא וחומרא
פרכינן כל דהו לא פרכינן. chada michada mikula vechumra parchinan kol dehu
lo parchinan. If you want to learn one from one, you have
one case that's a paradigm, then you could only be rejected if
there's if one case is more severe and the other's more lenient.
It's a good reason to reject, you know, that it doesn't apply
to the other case. כל דהו, kol dehu, we're going back, not
מליפף. mileifaf. If you say חדא מחדא chada michada is the case
of בנין אב. binyan av. If one case is a paradigm from
which you learn all others, then you could only way you would
not apply it to a particular case is if you said, oh,
that case was more severe, this case was more lenient, or that
case was more lenient, this case was more severe. But כל דהו,
kol dehu, a trivial way of rejecting it would not be good.
חדא מתרתי אפילו כל דהו פרכינן. chada mitartei afilu kol dehu parchinan.
When you learn from a מה הצד, mah hatzad, the common denominator
of two cases, then you can dismiss it with a trivial thing,
like oh, they grow from the ground. Okay, you know, even a
trivial way of dismissing it and therefore the rule doesn't apply here.
Learning from one is better than learning from two? Yes, because one
is a paradigm. Two, you know, the two, you're trying to say,
well, the common denominator is, how do you know that the common
denominator is really the rule? Maybe each one has its own rules.
So if you're trying to argue on the strength of common denominator,
even a trivial thing will allow you to dismiss it. However, חדא
מתלת, chada mitlat, one from three, which is our case, you've introduced
כלאים kilayim as well, אי הדר דינא ואתי במה הצד פרכינן כל
דהו ואי לא מקולא וחומרא פרכינן כל דהו לא פרכינן. i hadar
dina veati bemah hatzad parchinan kol dehu veilo mikula vechumra parchinan kol
dehu lo parchinan. If it goes, I'm not going to get into
the technicality of this, but basically it means if you go back
and make the whole thing a מה הצד mah hatzad between all
three of them, then you can still dismiss it with a trivial
question. But if in the end you wind up arguing not by
going back in the common denominator, remember כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem is
a good example because it's neither כרת kares nor is it אסור
assur from the beginning. So in the end you don't have to
make a common denominator. כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem serves as an example
in itself of not having either of those distinguishing characteristics and still
being אסור בהנאה. assur behanaah. So since it's not based on common
denominator, it's based on the strength of the example of כלאי הכרם,
kilay hakerem, you can't dismiss it trivially. So the upshot of all
of this is because of all three, you cannot dismiss the case
trivially, you have to have a good reason to dismiss it because
כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem is a sort of an example in itself
and it's not based on the common denominator, you can't just easily
just trivially dismiss it. And therefore we learn the principle, if you
can't eat, you can't derive benefit, like Rabbi Abahu's לא תאכל, and
therefore, if בשר בחלב is forbidden because it says אנשי קודש ותהיון
לי, anshei kodesh vehayitem li, and it says what's the פסוק by
בשר בחלב, כי עם קדוש אתה, so קודש kodesh means don't eat
forbidden food. And that's the עיקר, ikkar, the whole this whole thing
was also to get it to be forbidden in benefit. But let's
not forget the עיקר, which I think is an important point, you
know, that the concept of קדושה primarily a lot in the תורה
is about restraining from forbidden foods. So if it's being used by
בשר בחלב, the point is it's not just about not cooking them
together, it's also about not eating them together. Okay, good.